This was science in service to the public. This is what I came to graduate school for, and this is how I would rather spend my life. And so this coalition -- this unlikely coalition of citizens, pastors, journalists and scientists -- came together to uncover the truth using science, advocacy and activism. A local pediatrician figured out that the instances of childhood lead poisoning had indeed doubled in Flint during the crisis. And the state of Michigan was forced to acknowledge the problem and take steps to correct it. This group and many others got Flint's kids protected. A few months later, President Obama came in and declared a federal emergency, and now Flint is getting more than 600 million dollars in healthcare, nutrition, education and overhauling their water infrastructure. However, the arrogance and the callous disregard for public health shown by scientists and engineers at these government agencies is beyond belief. These unhealthy cultures that are festering in these groups, where the focus is on meeting regulations and checking boxes as opposed to protecting public health, is just appalling. Just consider this email that an EPA employee wrote, where she goes, "I'm not so sure Flint is a community we want to go out on a limb for." The dehumanization of an entire population could not be more obvious. Now, contrast that to the first canon of engineering, which, in my opinion, should be the first law of humanity: "To hold paramount the health, safety and welfare of the public," above all else. This is the Hippocratic Oath we've rarely acknowledged, let alone embraced. And so when scientists and engineers, very much like medical doctors, screw up, people can get hurt -- even die. If our professionals and even students fail to get that, society pays a huge price. Buried deep in history lies a character I deeply admire -- an engineer named Peter Palchinsky. He lived in the time of the Soviet Union. And Palchinsky repeatedly got in trouble for his radical honesty and willingness to point out major flaws in the Soviets' mindless pursuit of rapid industrialization. Everyone was expected to follow orders coming from the top. Anyone asking questions or offering feedback was unwelcome. The Soviets had created the largest army of engineers the world had ever seen, and yet most of them were mere cogs in a gigantic machine heading for doom. Palchinsky, on the other hand, implored engineers to look at the economic, political and social consequences of their actions; in other words, be more public-focused. His fearless voice of reason was seen as a threat to the political establishment, and Joseph Stalin had him executed in 1929. Palchinsky's view on technocrats is very different from one that is still very popular, still very common -- that of a dispassionate researcher working in his ivory tower lab, or a nerdy engineer working in his cubicle. Brilliant, no doubt, yet somehow cut off from the world, shows little emotion -- kind of like Spock from "Star Trek," you know? This guy. (Laughter) Let's try and do the Spock salute. I don't think I'll succeed ... See, I can't be Spock. Thank goodness I can't be Spock. (Laughter) I was reminded of this distinction because a recent article came out in a very reputed scientific journal, which kind of characterized our Flint work as driven by "youthful idealism," and "Hollywood's dramatic sensibilities." It asks scientists to protect their research funding and institutions at all costs, no matter how just the cause. And if you think you have to get involved in something, even if it's an emergency, try finding an activist group or an NGO, and obtain the full support of the academic community -- whatever that means -- before you get involved. Not one mention of our moral and professional obligation of preventing harm to the public, or the fact that we have all this expertise, resources and, for some, even tenure to, you know, accomplish this task. I'm not saying every scientist should be an activist. There are real and sometimes very painful consequences of speaking up. But to denounce this idea, this possibility so completely so that you can protect research funding, simply screams of self-serving cowardice, and these are not the ideals we would want to pass to our students. And so you may think, "OK, all this sounds great, but you'll never completely change organizational cultures, or imbibe mindsets in students and professionals to look at their work as a public good -- science in service to the public." Maybe so. But could a big reason for that be that we are not training our students right? Because if you look closely, our education system today is focused more on creating what ex-Yale professor Bill Deresiewicz calls "excellent sheep" -- young people who are smart and ambitious, and yet somehow risk-averse, timid, directionless and, sometimes, full of themselves. Now, kids ... you know, we fell in love with science when we were kids, and yet we somehow spend most of our time during high school and college just jumping through hoops and doing things so that we can polish our résumé instead of sitting down and reflecting on what we want to do and who we want to be. And so, the markers of empathy in our college graduates have been dropping dramatically in the past two decades, while those of narcissism are on the rise. There is also a growing culture of disengagement between engineering students and the public. We are trained to build bridges and solve complex problems but not how to think or live or be a citizen of this world. My undergraduate years were explicit job preparation, and I cannot tell you how suffocating and painful it was at times. And so, some people think the solution to great engineers, to great scientists, is more technical training. Maybe so. But where are the discussions on ethical decision-making, or building character, or discerning right from wrong? Consider this project that I deeply love and admire. It's called, "Heroic Imagination Project." A brainchild of Dr. Phil Zimbardo, famous for the Stanford Prison Experiment, this program seeks to train school-going children around the world to look at themselves as heroes-in-waiting, or heroes-in-training. So, these young minds work over time to develop skills and virtues so that when the opportunity comes, no matter what that opportunity be, to stand up and do the right thing. In other words, anyone can be a hero. Think about that idea for a second. Why don't we teach science and engineering like that -- where heroism and public service are seen as key values, because indeed, it's often heroism that is not only the antidote to public indifference, but also to systemic evil like we saw in Flint. And so, dream with me what a 21st-century scientist slash engineer could look like: individuals who are driven to master the sciences so that they can serve society, and are also aware of the tremendous power their knowledge and decisions have; folks who are developing their moral courage at all times, and who realize that conflict and controversy are not necessarily bad things if our ultimate loyalty is to the public and the planet. These are the people who will stand up like we did in Flint -- not to be saviors or heroes in the media, but altruistic and fundamentally good actors that you and I can trust. Imagine fostering such a public-focused mindset in classes, on service trips and during activities during college or even high school, so that these young minds will hold onto those ideals when they actually enter the real world, whether that be consulting, academia, policy making -- or even becoming the president of a country. Some of mankind's greatest challenges lie ahead of us; contaminated drinking water is just one example. We could definitely use more -- nay, we desperately need more -- compassionate upstanders and public-focused scientists and engineers who will strive to the do right thing, and not be easy to manage. Thank you. (Applause)
Esta era la ciencia de servicio al público. Para esto vine a la universidad y así es como preferiría pasar mi vida. Y así esta coalición... esta improbable coalición de ciudadanos, pastores, periodistas y científicos, se reunieron para descubrir la verdad utilizando ciencia, defensa y activismo. Un pediatra local descubrió que los casos de envenenamiento por plomo en la infancia se habían duplicado en Flint durante la crisis. Y el estado de Michigan se vio obligado a reconocer el problema y tomar medidas para corregirlo. Este grupo y muchos otros protegieron a los niños de Flint. Algunos meses después, el presidente Obama intervino y declaró una emergencia federal, y ahora Flint recibe más de USD 600 millones para salud, nutrición, educación y revisión de su infraestructura de agua. Sin embargo, la arrogancia y la indiferencia insensible por la salud pública demostrado por científicos e ingenieros en estas agencias gubernamentales va más allá de lo increíble. Estas culturas poco saludables que están pudriendo estos grupos, donde el foco está en cumplir regulaciones y cajas de verificación en contraposición a la protección de la salud pública, son simplemente espantosas. Simplemente vean este correo electrónico que escribió una empleada de la EPA, donde se lee: "No estoy tan segura de que queramos arriesgarnos por la comunidad de Flint". La deshumanización de toda una población no podría ser más obvia. Ahora, comparen eso con el primer canon de la ingeniería, que, en mi opinión, debe ser la primera ley de la humanidad: "Mantener primordialmente la salud, la seguridad y el bienestar del público", por encima de todo. Este es el juramento hipocrático que rara vez hemos reconocido, y mucho menos aplicado. Y así cuando los científicos e ingenieros, muy parecido a los médicos, hacen algo mal, haciendo que personas se vean perjudicadas, e incluso mueran, si nuestros profesionales e incluso estudiantes no consiguen eso, la sociedad paga un precio enorme. Enterrado en la historia hay un personaje al que admiro profundamente, un ingeniero llamado Peter Palchinsky. Vivió en la época de la Unión Soviética. Y Palchinsky se metió en problemas por su honestidad radical y su voluntad de señalar los principales defectos en el estúpido deseo de los soviéticos de una industrialización rápida. Todos esperaban que siguiera órdenes procedentes de los superiores. Cualquiera que hiciera preguntas o comentarios no era bienvenido. Los soviéticos habían creado el mayor ejército de ingenieros del mundo. Y, sin embargo, la mayoría eran meros engranajes en una gigantesca máquina camino a la catástrofe. Palchinsky, por otro lado, imploró a los ingenieros que examinaran las consecuencias económicas, políticas y sociales de sus acciones; en otras palabras, que se centraran más en el público. Su voz de la razón audaz fue vista como una amenaza al establecimiento político, y Joseph Stalin le hizo ejecutar en 1929. La opinión de Palchinsky sobre los tecnócratas es muy diferente a la de aquellos que sigue siendo muy popular y común, el de un investigador sin pasión que trabaja en su laboratorio en su torre de marfil, o de un ingeniero nerd que trabaja en su cubículo. Brillante, sin duda, pero de alguna manera sin conexión con el mundo, lo que muestra poca emoción, como Spock de "Star Trek". Este tipo. (Risas) Intentemos hacer el saludo de Spock. No creo que tenga éxito... Miren, no puedo ser Spock. Gracias a Dios no puedo ser Spock. (Risas) Me acordé de esta distinción por un artículo reciente que salió en una revista científica muy reputada, que caracterizó nuestro trabajo de Flint como impulsado por un "idealismo juvenil", y por "la sensibilidad dramática de Hollywood", pidiendo a científicos que protejan sus fondos e instituciones de investigación a toda costa, no importa la causa. Y si piensan que tienen que involucrarse en algo, incluso si es una emergencia, traten de encontrar un grupo de activistas o una ONG, y obtengan el apoyo total de la comunidad académica, lo que quiera que esto signifique, antes de involucrarse. Ni una mención de nuestra moral y la obligación profesional de prevenir el daño al público, o el hecho de que tener toda esta experiencia, recursos y, para algunos, incluso tenencia para realizar esta tarea. No estoy diciendo que cada científico deba ser un activista. Hay consecuencias reales y a veces muy dolorosas al hablar. Pero para denunciar esta idea, esta posibilidad para poder proteger la financiación de la investigación, simplemente gritos de cobardía egoísta, y estos no son los ideales que queríamos dar a nuestros estudiantes. Y Uds. pueden pensar: "Bien, todo esto suena genial, pero nunca cambiará completamente las culturas organizativas, o adoctrinar pensamientos en estudiantes y profesionales para mirar su trabajo como bien público, la ciencia al servicio del público. Tal vez sea así. Pero ¿una gran razón de eso podría ser que no estamos entrenando a nuestros estudiantes correctamente? Porque si miran de cerca, nuestro sistema de educación hoy se centra más en la creación lo que el exprofesor de Yale Bill Deresiewicz llama "oveja excelente", jóvenes inteligentes y ambiciosos, que sin embargo temen al riesgo, son tímidos, no tienen dirección y, a veces, ensimismados. Ahora, los niños... ya saben, nos enamoramos de la ciencia cuando éramos niños, y, sin embargo, pasamos la mayor parte del tiempo en la secundaria y universidad simplemente saltando a través de aros y haciendo cosas para pulir nuestro curriculum vitae en lugar de sentarse y reflexionar sobre lo que queremos hacer y qué queremos ser. Y así, los marcadores de empatía en nuestros graduados universitarios han estado cayendo dramáticamente en las últimas dos décadas, Mientras que las del narcisismo están en aumento. También hay una creciente cultura de la desconexión entre estudiantes de ingeniería y el público. Estamos entrenados para construir puentes y resolver problemas complejos pero no en cómo pensar o vivir o ser un ciudadano de este mundo. Mis años de pregrado fueron la preparación explícita al trabajo, y no puedo decir lo sofocante y doloroso que fue a veces. Y así, algunos piensan que la solución para grandes ingenieros y científicos, es más formación técnica. Tal vez sea así. Pero ¿dónde están las discusiones sobre la toma de decisiones éticas o de formar carácter, o de discernir entre el bien del mal? Miren este proyecto que amo y admiro profundamente. Se llama "Proyecto de Imaginación Heroica". Una idea original del Dr. Phil Zimbardo, famoso por el experimento de la prisión de Stanford, este programa busca entrenar a niños escolares de todo el mundo a mirarse a sí mismos como héroes en estado latente, o héroes en formación. Así, estas mentes jóvenes trabajan para desarrollar habilidades y virtudes para que cuando llegue la oportunidad, no importa cuál sea esa oportunidad, se pongan en pie y hagan lo correcto. En otras palabras, cualquier persona puede ser un héroe. Piensen en esa idea por un segundo. ¿Por qué no enseñamos ciencia e ingeniería de esa manera donde el heroísmo y el servicio público son vistos como valores clave? Porque de hecho, a menudo es heroísmo que no es solo el antídoto a la indiferencia pública, sino también al mal sistemático como vimos en Flint. Y así, sueño lo que un científico o ingeniero del siglo XXI podría llegar a ser: individuos motivados a dominar las ciencias para servir a la sociedad, y también para ser conscientes del tremendo poder que tienen sus conocimientos y decisiones; personas que están desarrollando su valor moral en todo momento, y que se dan cuenta de que el conflicto y la controversia no son necesariamente cosas malas si nuestra lealtad final es para el público y el planeta. Estas son las personas que se pondrán de pie como lo hicimos en Flint, no siendo salvadores o héroes en los medios de comunicación, sino altruistas y fundamentalmente buenos actores en los que poder confiar. Imaginen fomentar esta mentalidad centrada en el público en clase, en viajes de servicio y durante actividades durante la universidad o incluso en la escuela secundaria, para que estas jóvenes mentes se aferren a esos ideales cuando realmente entren al mundo real, ya sea en consultoría, en la academia, la formulación de políticas, o incluso lleguen a ser presidentes de un país. Algunos de los mayores desafíos de la humanidad se encuentran ante nosotros; el agua potable contaminada es solo un ejemplo. Podríamos definitivamente usar más, no, necesitamos desesperadamente más, luchadores compasivos y científicos e ingenieros enfocados al público que se esforzarán para hacer lo correcto, y no ser fáciles de manejar. Gracias. (Aplausos)